Good morning.
My name is Dan Margulis. I'm filling in for Rabbi Linzer while
he's away this week.
He is on vacation, a much and much deserved vacation. Today's דף
daf is going to be בבא קמא פג, Bava Kamma Pe Gimmel,
83. He's on vacation from the דף? daf? I'm sure he will
be learning דף יומי daf yomi while he's on vacation, but he's
not able to teach the דף יומי daf yomi while he's on
vacation. Today's the 18th day of אב Av and it's the 22nd
of August and summer is starting to wind down. All right. We
are going to start on the
exactly the last line on פב עמוד ב. Pe Bet Amud Bet.
The משנה mishna had discussed the fact that it is forbidden to
raise pigs.
Always interesting to think in other cultures, they would have to talk
about חכמת יוונית, chochmat yevanit, so we'll have to talk about חכמת
יוונית. chochmat yevanit. In the Odyssey, at the end, Odysseus returns home
and the two different people from his household who he's interacting with
extensively are the swineherd and the shepherd. And obviously the relationship
that he has with the different people who watch the different animals,
but the swineherd becomes this like very prominent character in the end
of the Odyssey. Obviously, Jewish tradition we don't have any swineherds to
have as good characters in our stories; all of our good characters
are shepherds. So okay. The גמרא Gemara says: חכמת יוונית מי אסר?
chochmat yevanit mi asar? So the previous part of the גמרא Gemara
which we had read yesterday had already noted that there was this
גזירה gezeira instituted during the time of the Hasmonean dynasty, during the
time of the חשמונאים, Chashmonaim, or perhaps later, perhaps during the time
of the חורבן churban around the time of the Roman rule, that
it would be prohibited for someone to teach their child חכמת יוונית,
chochmat yevanit, the wisdom of the Greeks, Greek wisdom. So we're going
to have to see now what is that referring to. We know
the גמרא Gemara has a range of opinions about the value of
the Greek language and the Greek intellectual pursuits. We saw a few
weeks ago the גמרא Gemara in בבא קמא Bava Kamma itself quotes
some אמוראים amora'im quote from Aesop's fables. So certainly חז"ל Chazal and
the rabbis and the general populace were familiar with many of these
things. The question is how much of a positive influence or a
good thing they are to be studying and how much...
and they write the ספר תורה Sefer Torah in יוונית. Yevanit.
Right, you can write the... exactly. The גמרא Gemara מגילה Megillah discusses
based on the פסוק pasuk in the end of פרשת נח. Parshat
Noach. The פסוק pasuk says יפת אלוהים ליפת וישכון באהלי
שם. Yaft Elokim l'Yefet v'yishkon b'oholei Shem. אלוהים, Elokim, right. That's exactly
the point, it's אלוהים, Elokim, right.
So he says, you have so many words that are
based, there are many Greek words, but also that there is a
notion at least among people who themselves spoke Greek that Greek was
a good language to be used for Torah study or conversations. So
we're going to see here.
Just to note, תוספות Tosafot deals with the question of when did
this גזירה gezeira get instituted? Was it during the Hasmonean period? Was
it during the Roman period? And תוספות Tosafot says at one point
they made the גזירה gezeira and maybe the גזירה gezeira really didn't
kick in or wasn't popular until much later. That is, we know
the general principle that if people are unable to keep the גזירה
gezeira then the סנהדרין Sanhedrin doesn't really have the power to institute
it to begin with, the sense of גזירה שאין הציבור יכול לעמוד
בה. gezeira she'ein hatzibur yachol la'amod bah.
And then alternatively, תוספות Tosafot suggests that there is a difference between
what this גמרא Gemara had said here and it says ארור האדם
שילמד את
בנו חכמת יוונית.
Arur ha'adam she'ylamed et
bno chochmat yevanit.
A person who teaches their child Greek wisdom should be cursed and
the גרסא girsa that's quoted in תוספות Tosafot אסור לאדם שילמד בנו
חכמת יוונית. Asur l'adam she'ylamed bno chochmat yevanit. Is there a prohibition
or is it not prohibited but you'll get cursed if you do
it?
Most people would prefer not to get cursed anyway. We're going to
see that getting cursed is going to be a נפקא מינה nafkamina
later on the next עמוד. amud. It's just interesting to note those
two different versions. So the גמרא Gemara says: חכמת יוונית מי אסר?
chochmat yevanit mi asar?
Is חכמת יוונית chochmat yevanit really forbidden? והתניא, ve'hatanya, but we have
this ברייתא braita that says: אמר רבי, amar Rabbi, רבי יהודה הנשיא
Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi said: בארץ ישראל, be'Eretz Yisrael,
לשון סורסאי למה? lashon sursai lama? Why do they speak this Sursian
language? Now we don't know what that means.
According to רש"י Rashi it seems to just be speaking in an
unclear way perhaps, הוא לשון צח וסרסורי לשון נלעז הוא, hu lashon
zach ve'sarsuri lashon nil'az hu,
it's confusing but Greek is very clear. תוספות Tosafot says סורסאי sursai
just means Aramaic, but it means the Palestinian Aramaic, the Aramaic spoken
in the Land of Israel that רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi
was familiar with, the Aramaic of the ירושלמי Yerushalmi and of the
תרגום Targum compared to what's going to be called לשון ארמי, lashon
arami, which is going to be the Aramaic of the תלמוד בבלי.
Talmud Bavli. Different dialect. רבי Rabbi was in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
רבי Rabbi was in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, exactly. So he says,
in the Land of Israel, it's not...
is it Syriac? Ah, perhaps. Syriac I think is a
kind of, it's like the, you know, the ancient,
Syriac, the western. Well, let's see what רב יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda
HaNasi says. He says, אמר רבי: Amar Rabbi: בארץ ישראל, be'Eretz Yisrael,
לשון סורסי למה? lashon sursi lama? Why did they speak this לשון
סורסי? lashon sursi? או לשון הקודש, o lashon hakodesh, או לשון יוונית.
o lashon yovanit. They should either speak Hebrew Hebrew, like real Hebrew,
לשון הקודש, Lashon HaKodesh, biblical Hebrew, or they should speak לשון יוונית,
Lashon Yovanit, the Greek language. So obviously speaking Greek is perfectly fine.
The Greek language. Interesting why is Hebrew called לשון הקודש, Lashon HaKodesh,
a very important מחלוקת machloket between the רמב"ם Rambam and רמב"ן. Ramban.
The רמב"ם Rambam in מורה נבוכים Moreh Nevuchim says the reason Hebrew
is called לשון הקודש Lashon HaKodesh is because it doesn't have what
we would say vulgar words, dirty words, curse words. It doesn't have
those kinds of words. So the language is, it speaks pure in
a sense of euphemism. That is things that we would prefer not
to say explicitly, there's no way to say explicitly. Even things like
the sexual act for example is called ביאה, biah, it just means
entering in. It's not really a description of what's going on, it's
a euphemism.
Compared to other languages which have specific words for those sorts of
things. רמב"ן Ramban obviously disagrees with the רמב"ם. Rambam. רמב"ן Ramban in
פרשת כי תשא Parshat Ki Tisa says the reason why Hebrew is
called לשון הקודש Lashon HaKodesh is because that's the language that God
wrote the תורה Torah in. That's the language that angels speak. That's
the language that God speaks in. That's the language that is the
language of creation and has an intrinsic holiness. So what the phrase
לשון הקודש Lashon HaKodesh means, is it about how we relate to
the language and how we can use it, or is it about
something to do with God directly? Interestingly of course the רמב"ם Rambam
obviously wouldn't attribute the use of a human language to God. So
obviously that's רמב"ן Ramban is willing to have that anthropomorphous sense because
it imbues the language with a direct holiness, but it's an interesting
question. Okay, אמר רבי יוסי. Amar Rabbi Yosi. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
has a similar approach to בבל. Bavel. He says, בבל, Bavel, לשון
ארמי למה? lashon arami lama? Why do they speak this Aramaic language?
או לשון הקודש, o lashon hakodesh, או לשון פרסי. o lashon parsi.
They should either speak Hebrew or they should speak Persian, they should
speak Farsi. So meaning the Aramaic language seemingly here from both perspectives
is like, okay, what's the real value of it? Now we know
in other places חז"ל Chazal talk about how wonderful the Aramaic language
is. It's the only language which appears in the תורה Torah besides
Hebrew, describing לבן, Lavan, the words יגר שהדותא Yegar Sahaduta is the
Aramaic translation of גלעד. Galed. And also we know that obviously the
fact that the Jewish people used it, the fact that the תלמודים
Talmuds were written in Aramaic, the fact that the תרגומים targumim were
written into Aramaic means that it has some significance. So just an
interesting change of perspective. These rabbis are obviously saying Greek and also
Persian being the language of the ruling dynasty at the time and
that location and a useful language, but also clear, elegant language, perfectly
reasonable to know and to learn. So then what's the problem of
חכמת יוונית? chochmat yovanit? So the גמרא Gemara says,
לשון יוונית לחוד חכמת יוונית לחוד. lashon yovanit lachud chochmat yovanit lachud.
There's a difference between the Greek language and the Greek wisdom. Now
we still don't know what it means Greek wisdom. Maybe it means
philosophy, maybe it means Greek literature, maybe it means something to do
with some of those things, not really sure. They haven't told us,
probably because they don't want us to know.
So what do they say? וחכמת יוונית מי אסירא? vechochmat yovanit mi
asira? And still the גמרא Gemara asks further, who said that חכמת
יוונית chochmat yovanit is אסור? asur? Meaning we already rejected the notion
that the Greek language should be אסור asur to learn and now
we're going to even combat the question of whether the Greek wisdom
is אסור asur to learn. It says, והאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל
משום רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. veha'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel mishum Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel. So רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, the אמורא Amora very
late, is quoting from רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
who was one of the תנאים. Tannaim. So it's actually a very
long tradition. He says
a מדרש midrash actually on a פסוק pasuk from איכה, Eicha, from
the third chapter of איכה, Eicha, עיני עוללה לנפשי מכל בנות עירי.
eini olela linafshi mikol benot iri. My eye is most wailing for
itself out of all of the daughters of the city. And he
says רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, he's the son
of רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. What does he say? אלף ילדים היו
בבית אבא. elef yeladim hayu be'veit aba. There were one thousand children
in my father's house, probably it means not just רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel's children, but the students of his household and the people who
were part of his,
he had a school or he had a community perhaps. And he
says חמש מאות מהם למדו תורה, chamesh me'ot mehem lamdu Torah, five
hundred went to study תורה. Torah. חמש מאות למדו חכמת יוונית, chamesh
me'ot lamdu chochmat yovanit, and the other half, five hundred went to
learn Greek wisdom. ולא נשתייר מהם אלא אני וכאן ובן אחי אבא
באסיא.
velo nishtayer mehem ela
ani vekan uven achi aba be'Asya. And the only ones who are
left after the חורבן, churban, that is many of them or almost
all of them, nine hundred and ninety-eight of those one thousand children
perished in the חורבן. churban. The only ones who survived are me
myself and my cousin who lives in אסיא. Asya. And so therefore
sounds like you had a perfectly good choice, you could either go
study תורה Torah or you could go study חכמת יוונית chochmat yovanit
if you're in רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel's house. So what's the justification
for that? שאני בית רבן גמליאל שהיו קרובים למלכות. shani beit Rabban
Gamliel she'hayu krovim lamalchut. No, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel's family had political
power, they had to be able to have conversations with the Roman
government and to be able to have those kind of interactions, so
that's a... A permission for them to study to study חכמת יוונית
Chochmas Yevanis because of קרוב, karov, they were קרובים למלכות. kerovim lamalchus.
They were close to the ruling class. And we know throughout Jewish
history and throughout הלכה, halacha, there are often exceptions that have been
made to certain kinds of הלכות halachos for people who need to
have that flexibility to be able to interact with the non-Jewish authorities.
One of the main examples is what? Well יוסף Yosef obviously. יוסף
Yosef shaved his beard, יוסף Yosef shaved off his shaved off his
פאות peyos and all sorts of things.
Some of the things that אסתר Esther had to do when she
was in the palace have been justified in a similar way. Fascinating
question is does this only apply to דרבנןs de'rabbanan or even to
דאורייתאs? de'oraysa That is the חכמת יוונית Chochmas Yevanis question we saw
was a גזירה gezeira that the rabbis made. So if the rabbis
made the גזירה, gezeira, then they could make exceptions to it. They
could say it's allowed in the case of קרוב למלכות. karov lamalchus.
But interestingly enough, we're going to see the next example. What does
the next example say? וכדתניא המספר קומי הרי זה מדרכי האמורי. U'kedisanya
hamisaper kumi harei zeh midarchei ha'Emori. If you get this certain kind
of haircut, a קומי kumi haircut, then that's מדרכי האמורי, midarchei ha'Emori,
that's Amorite ways which are forbidden. That's a code word in חז"ל,
Chazal, in the תוספתא, Tosefta, in the משנה, Mishna, for describing all
sorts of things, usually with a magical basis, but more generally something
associated with עבודה זרה, avoda zara, something associated with idolatry. Or a
בולרית, bularit, בולרית bularit is a different kind of a haircut which
is also prohibited.
So if you got this certain kind of haircut, that's prohibited because
it identifies you as someone not Jewish or you look you're trying
to look like someone non-Jewish or trying to look like one of
the priests of the עבודה זרה, avoda zara, something like that. Okay,
but
so אבטולמוס בן ראובן, Avtulumos ben Reuven, אבטולמוס Avtulumos the son of
ראובן, Reuven, התירו לו לספר קומי. hitiro lo lesaper kumi. The rabbis
allowed him to get this kind of haircut. Why? מפני שהוא קרוב
למלכות mipnei she'hu karov lamalchus because he was close with the Roman
government. The גמרא Gemara in מעילה Me'ilah notes actually that his son,
ראובן בן אבטולמוס, Reuven ben Avtulumos, was involved in many of the
conversations with the Romans as well. So the fact is, you know,
this family had obviously prominence with the with the government. Okay, so
התירו לו לספר קומי מפני שהוא קרוב למלכות של בית רבן גמליאל
התירו להם לספר בחכמת יוונית. hitiro lo lesaper kumi mipnei she'hu karov
lamalchus shel Beis Rabban Gamliel hitiro lahem lesaper be'Chochmas Yevanis. And the
the family of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel they allowed them interestingly of
course the pun almost לספר lesaper to get a haircut and לספר
lesaper to speak to tell the stories לספר בחכמת יוונית מפני שהיו
קרובים למלכות. lesaper be'Chochmas Yevanis mipnei she'hayu kerovim lamalchus. So they could
discuss חכמת יוונית Chochmas Yevanis because they had to be able to
you know it's like well I need to be able to have
something to talk about when I go to the you know to
have even casual conversation or to be up to date on those
kind of cultural points to be able to have those conversations so
they won't think you're some kind of who doesn't know חכמת יוונית.
Chochmas Yevanis. So we still don't know what חכמת יוונית Chochmas Yevanis
is. It's probably something that you're לספר lesaper that you tell a
story, so perhaps I was saying perhaps that's an indication that it
has something to do with the Greek literature, but it's not not
for sure. Important point is one second, if we said that the
haircut problem is מדרכי האמורי, midarchei ha'Emori, that category is בחוקותיהם לא
תלכו. be'chukoseihem lo seleichu. We're not allowed to follow the ways of
non-Jewish nations that are characteristically identify one as as acting in a
non-Jewish way.
The question is to what things does that apply? So interestingly enough
כסף משנה Kesef Mishneh in order to explain this exception, how can
you say קרוב למלכות karov lamalchus is an exception for דרכי האמורי
darchei ha'Emori if it's a דאורייתא de'oraysa prohibition? It must be that
and he applies a principle that's not applied in the גמרא Gemara
to this but he extends it.
Whatever's mentioned in the תורה Torah you think so it's not any
עניין. inyan.
But it's not just what's mentioned in the תורה Torah it's actually
מסרו הכתוב לחכמים. masro hakasuv lachachamim. The rabbis get to determine the
parameters of what is דאורייתא. de'oraysa. That is the תורה Torah has
a prohibition, a very general prohibition. There are many things that fall
under that prohibition including this kind of haircut. But the rabbis were
able to say if you're קרוב למלכות karov lamalchus you don't have
to worry about that kind of haircut.
That's very dangerous.
It's very dangerous. It's like you can't go to college, דרכי האמורי.
darchei ha'Emori. So the next question is the מהרי"ק. Maharik. The מהרי"ק
Maharik has an opinion which is quoted in שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch
where he talks about the big question in his day was if
you go to university can you wear the academic robes? This was
like the late Middle Ages I guess or very early מהרי"ק Maharik
of
קולון Cologne is like
14th 15th century, 15th century, 1400s. So
that's like the late Renaissance.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So the מהרי"ק Maharik was asked
he's already 200 years old.
Right. So he was asked this question could you wear academic robes
when you go to the university? And he said there's two different
kinds of things
that בחוקותיהם be'chukoseihem could apply to. There are things which are totally
illogical and have no reason. That's what's prohibited because then the only
reason you would be doing it is to impersonate a non-Jew or
to blend into non-Jewish society. But something that makes a lot of
sense why you would do it like if you have an advanced
degree wearing the clothes of that
of that like
you wear a
doctor, you wear the collar right you wear the right.
You have this degree so you wear that robe. Or you work
in this field, so you wear that kind of, kind of hat
or something like that, so those kind of things would be allowed
because that's for business, that's professional garb.
Okay, but this doesn't answer the haircut thing.
So the haircut thing is the, is the כסף משנה Kesef Mishneh
which says חז"ל Chazal had the right to make exceptions for that
too. Yeah, and he actually, and the מהרי"ק Maharik's תשובה teshuvah becomes
the basis for so much more of the discussion about בחוקותיהם bechukoteihem
much later, which got extended to questions,
one of the biggest modern discussions of בחוקותיהם bechukoteihem becomes the question
dealt with in the שרידי אש, Seridei Esh, I think, about the
בת מצוה. bat mitzvah. How much is having a בת מצוה bat
mitzvah celebration בחוקותיהם bechukoteihem or not?
Does the גמרא Gemara mention having בת מצוה? bat mitzvah?
Well, obviously the non-Jewish people are not having בת מצוה, bat mitzvahs,
but the question was if non-observant Jewish communities who are having it,
how do you get from that to בחוקותיהם? bechukoteihem? It's very dangerous
territory.
But that's where the conversation comes and through that he has a
whole long discussion of what בחוקותיהם bechukoteihem is about more broadly as
well. Okay, the גמרא Gemara continues. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. לא יגדל
אדם את ה-... lo yegadel adam et ha-... okay, so the משנה
Mishnah had said, לא יגדל אדם את הכלב אלא אם כן קשור
בשלשלת. lo yegadel adam et hakelev ela im kein kashur beshalshelet. A
person should not raise a dog unless it is attached to a
chain or to a leash or some kind. Presumably always, presumably the
dog should be restrained in some way that it cannot escape. Now
obviously חז"ל, Chazal, as I think we're going to see, the discussion
here is about first of all a dog who lives outdoors, not
about a dog who lives indoors. A dog who is constrained to
living indoors anyway can't escape. The question is how is a dog
going to run.
But I'm worried about like its barking and intimidating people and even
if it is indoors.
But a dog can bark even if it's chained up.
But if it's behind a door and it's chained up then the
noise will be far less. You've been to houses, you walk
in, dog jumps all over someone. Okay, so we'll see. So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. The Rabbis
taught in a ברייתא. Baraisa. לא יגדל אדם את הכלב אלא אם
כן קשור בשלשלת. lo yegadel adam et hakelev ela im kein kashur
beshalshelet. A person should not raise a dog unless it is attached
to a chain. אבל מגדל הוא בעיר הסמוכה לספר. aval megadel hu
be'ir hasmucha lesefar. ספר, Sefar,
the borderlands.
ספר Sefar would be the book,
right?
I've heard it pronounced ספר, sefer, could be ספר, sefar, whatever it
is. A person could raise a dog if you live in the
border town. That is, even if it's not chained up, the dog
could be left off the chain some of the times if you
live in the border, why? To protect the border. The same reason
we're not allowed to make עיר הנדחת ir hanidachat at the border
because it would reduce the territory of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So
too, to have a vicious dog who's on the loose in the
border territory will prevent people from trying to encroach on our cities.
Yes.
What's the pun here between ספר, sefar, ספר, sefer, and ספר? sapar?
Yeah, there's, it's a mnemonic pun. It's to help with the סוגיות.
sugyot.
It's extraordinarily clever.
It's very clever because what they did is they were discussing pigs,
they went into חכמה יוונית chochma yevanit which went into haircuts, which
comes back to now to dogs which was the next part of
the משנה. Mishnah. So it's really a very elegantly woven סוגיא. sugya.
Okay, so the הלכה halacha is that you are allowed to raise
a dog in the borderlands city, דקושרו ביום ומתירו בלילה, dekoshro bayom
umatiro balaila, as long as the dog is tied up during the
day, you could release the dog at night time. To deter intruders.
To deter intruders, right. The people know, you know, my dog is
roaming the streets at night, they're going to be less inclined to
come try to encroach on my territory. Okay.
So תניא. Tanya. רבי אליעזר הגדול Rabbi Eliezer Hagadol אומר, omer, המגדל
כלבים כמגדל חזירים. hamegadel kelavim kemegadel chazirim. He takes a much more
negative approach to dogs. If you raise dogs, it's like raising pigs.
Okay, so we saw someone who raises pigs, it's said ארור המגדל
חזיר בארץ ישראל, arur hamegadel chazir be'Eretz Yisrael, right, you're
not allowed to, it's cursed is a person who raises pigs in
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So raising a dog is comparable. Why? Because
it basically serves no purpose in terms of the Jewish lifestyle. There's
no real reason in חז"ל Chazal's mindset to have a dog. What
was the purpose of having a dog? It was either for hunting,
which Jews wouldn't be doing, or maybe it's to protect your sheep.
So that's a good reason to have a dog, I think, from
חז"ל Chazal's mindset. But if you're just like you make your business
raising and selling dogs, you know, like why do you do that?
That's basically his point.
They didn't have pets.
They didn't have pets, exactly. We're talking about working animals, and modern
pets are obviously different, a different question entirely. So he says המגדל
כלבים כמגדל חזירים. hamegadel kelavim kemegadel chazirim. למאי נפקא מינה? Lemai nafka
mina?
So what's the difference between that opinion and the opinion that just
says it's forbidden to raise a dog unless it's chained up? It
says למקיים עליו בארור. lemekayeim alav be'arur. Because if you raise pigs,
it's really ארור, arur, it's cursed. Raising dogs, nobody ever said it
was cursed until רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer came along. Interesting to note,
if you consider that previous תוספות, Tosafot, which is worse, right? Which
is worse? ארור Arur or just אסור? assur? So here it sounds
like, oh, it was אסור assur but it wasn't ארור. arur. It's
forbidden but you weren't cursed for it, and then he comes along
and says even you get, even you get the curse. The previous
עמוד, amud, תוספות Tosafot seemed to take the opposite approach, that ארור
arur could be, you could say someone is cursed for doing something
even if it's permitted. So it's kind of an interesting balance. Okay.
So you're saying modern פוסקים poskim differentiated between?
I think, again, I own a dog. So the פוסקים poskim I've
spoken to would say that the הלכות halachot involving raising a dog,
we're going to see obviously... Obviously a כלב רע, kelev ra, a
vicious dog, is prohibited to raise. So you have to make sure
you train the dog to be safe and to not attack people.
Number two: the dog should be restrained when in public. It shouldn't
just be allowed to run around in the street. I think this
הלכה halacha still applies, the sense of like not letting the dog
just wander around in public streets. So yeah, I think those הלכות
halachot still do apply. There's obviously a responsible way to raise a
dog even if it's a safe, friendly, happy dog.
But not necessarily in your backyard.
In your backyard is רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. It's different.
No, but again, you
they had, you know, oh, but they didn't have fences around their
backyard! Like everything was... anyway, fine. So I don't know about that.
I don't have a backyard, I live in an apartment. Okay.
אמר רב יוסף בר מניומי אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Yosef bar
Minyumi amar Rav Nachman, כל עיר הסמוכה לספר. kol ir hasmucha lesefar.
So,
so what, oh sorry, בבל כעיר הסמוכה לספר דמי. Bavel ke'ir hasmucha
lesefar dami. בבל, Bavel, that is not the entire nation of בבל,
Bavel, Babylonia, but רש"י Rashi points us בבל Bavel meaning the city
of נהרדעא, Nehardea, which was the, the great city of בבל. Bavel.
So נהרדעא, Nehardea, which was also called בבל, Bavel, that city is
like a city on the border regarding this הלכה halacha that you're
allowed to let your dog off the leash at nighttime. Actually I
think that's the הלכה halacha in Central Park as well if I'm
not mistaken. Okay. תרגמה נהרדעא Targema Nehardea and
and that's exactly what it is. Is it on the border or?
Well either because it was on the border, or if you take
a look in רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi actually has a very interesting
suggestion for what we have nowadays. What do we consider to be
like a Jewish town? Look in
רש"י Rashi בבל: Bavel: שם המדינה ועיר אחת שבה נקראת נהרדעא ואותה
העיר סמוכה לספר והשמיענו רב נחמן דכל שיש בבבל יישוב קבוע.
Shem hamedina ve'ir achat sheba nikret Nehardea ve'ota
ha'ir smucha lesefar vehashmi'anu Rav Nachman dechol sheyesh beVavel yishuv kavua. It
has a permanent settlement. וישראל הרבה, veYisrael harbe, and there are many
Jews there. So then מותר לגדל כלבים בעיר הסמוכה לספר כאילו היא
בארץ ישראל. mutar legadel kelavim ba'ir hasmucha lesefar ke'ilu hi be'Eretz Yisrael.
So you treat בבל Bavel like ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael regarding this
הלכה halacha as long as you have two criteria: permanent settlement, it's
not people who are living there only temporarily, and number two: there
are many Jews. So perhaps you could say the same thing about
Riverdale. Or maybe you don't have as many Jews as נהרדעא Nehardea
did. But maybe, you know, parts of Brooklyn, parts of Manhattan perhaps,
certainly parts of New Jersey are areas with a permanent settlement of
Jews, a well-established Jewish community. And the sense is that again, our
relationship with our neighboring towns is very different than they had back
then, but the sense you don't want people encroaching in your town.
So if the people in Teaneck are worried the people in Englewood
are going to come in, you know, invade, so they could release
the dogs at night to perhaps... okay.
Okay. But it's interesting, those two criteria: יישוב קבוע, yishuv kavua, permanent
settlement, and ישראל הרבה, Yisrael harbe, many Jews. So that's what makes
בבל Bavel like ישראל. Yisrael. Obviously בבל Bavel in no way is
actually like Israel, but they had to do their best. Okay. דרש
רבי דוסתאי דמן בירי: Darash Rabi Dostai demin Biri: ובנחה
יאמר שובה ה' רבבות אלפי ישראל. uvnucho yomar shuva Hashem rivvot alfei
Yisrael. The פסוק pasuk says when the ארון aron would rest, they
would cry out or משה Moshe would cry out that God should
return, return with or return to the רבבות, rivvot, the tens of
thousands, אלפי ישראל, alfei Yisrael, of thousands of ישראל. Yisrael. Now תוספות
Tosafot points out in the desert there were not tens of thousands
of thousands of Jews because ten thousand times one thousand is a
million and we know that there were only six hundred thousand. So
that calculation is not meant to be taken as a multiplication, but
addition. רבבות rivvot is twenty thousand, two ten thousands, and אלפי, alfei,
again, אלפים, alafim, plural, so two thousand. He says למדך שאין שכינה
שורה על ישראל פחות משני אלפים ושני רבבות. lamedcha she'ein Shechina shora
al Yisrael pachot mishnei alafim ushnei rivvot.
The שכינה Shechina does not descend and dwell amongst the Jewish people
unless there are twenty-two thousand Jewish people present. Okay, so maybe that's
our threshold. How many Jewish people live in Riverdale?
Question, I don't know.
Okay, but רבבות, rivvot, which
he talks about...
Ah, you're asking
תוספות's Tosafot's question!
Even one, even two, even three, even ten! So obviously there are
different amounts of the שכינה Shechina that you could have. We know
that there's a certain level of the שכינה's Shechina's presence when there
are six hundred thousand Jews present, like at מעמד הר סיני. Ma'amad
Har Sinai. There's a special ברכה bracha for that. Twenty-two thousand, this
גמרא Gemara says is important. Less than that, well ten obviously, if
there are ten Jewish men you have a מנין. minyan. For ten
Jewish people you have קידוש השם. Kiddush Hashem. If there are three,
you have a זימון. zimmun. If there are two, you can have
a חברותא. chavruta. If there's even one person alone studying, there's still
God comes and joins in with the learning. So obviously there are
different levels of how much the שכינה Shechina could be present. But
here he says twenty-two thousand. Okay. So what if it was חסר
אחת? chasar achat? What if there was one person missing? What if
it was twenty-one thousand nine hundred ninety-nine
people? והייתה שם עוברת ביניהם, Vehayta sham uberet beneihem, and there was
a pregnant woman who's about to give birth. That is, so the
twenty-two thousandth Jewish person will become here, will be here in just
a few minutes, and therefore the שכינה Shechina is going to come.
הראויה להשלים, har'uya lehashlim,
she's going to fill out the number. ונבח בה כלב, venavach bah
kelev,
and the dog snapped at her. והפילה, vehipila, and she had a
miscarriage. miscarriage at that point, and the child was not alive in
order to fulfill that 22,000. נמצא זה גורם לשכינה שתסתלק מישראל. nimtza
zeh gorem lash'china shetistalek miYisrael.
Therefore the dog having snapped at her, a vicious dog barking, is
what caused the שכינה Shechinah to not come and visit the Jewish
people.
Well, that sounds like a reversal of what you do with a
problem.
Exactly, that seems to be exactly the suggestion of רבי אליעזר הגדול.
Rabbi Eliezer Hagadol. That is, the presence of a dog can cause
complications that in the end will cause the שכינה Shechinah to be
separated from the Jewish people. ההיא אתתא דעללה למיפא בההוא ביתא, ha'hi
it'ta de'al'la lemifa behahu beita, a woman was coming to bake in
someone's house. We know that we saw this already previously in the
מסכתא, Massekta, that the women would come to grind their wheat in
their friend's house or they would come to bake in their friend's
house. People, different people had different parts of the process. Maybe somebody
had a millstone and somebody had an oven, or different things—they were
shared. So people would go over to each other's house to cook.
Okay, so this woman went to someone's house to bake. נבח בה
כלבא, navach bah kalba, and the dog snapped at her. אמר לה
מרה לא תדחלי מיניה שקולי ניביה,
amar lah marei lo
tid'chali minei shakuli nivyei,
so like the owner of the dog said, don't worry about it.
Bark's worse than his bite.
Something like that. He says, take the
teeth out—not fangs, but the canine teeth out—so take them out and
throw them in the trash. So she says, אמרה ליה שקולי טיבותך
ושדיא אחיזרי, amrah lei shekuli tivutach veshadei achizrei, like take away your
good
wishes and throw them to the pigs.
כבר נד ולד, kevar nad velad, that is, we've already had the
connection with pigs and dogs. And so she says, כבר נד ולד,
kevar nad velad, that is, once the dog had barked, the child
had already somehow turned over in her womb—she knew that it was
going to be a miscarriage, and at that point she said you
can't comfort me by telling me, oh don't worry about it, the
dog is going to not be a problem. It's important to consider
the way רש"י Rashi frames it—take a look in
רש"י—טיבותך, שקולי טיבותך, shekuli tivutach, take away your good wishes. נטולה היא
טובתך ומוטלת על הקוצים, netulah hi tovat'cha umutelet al hakotzim, like your
good wishes thrown onto the thorns. מה אתה מנחמני הבל, ma atah
menachameni havel, why are you wishing me good נחמה, nechamah, good consolation?
It's totally worthless. הבל, havel, it's totally worthless. I think this is
one of the קינות, Kinnot, actually, is called מה אתה מנחמני הבל,
ma atah menachameni havel, at least in Ashkenazic קינות, Kinnot, I think.
And also it's interesting to note, you know, we think about going
to a בית אבל Beit Avel and things like that, there are
certain periods of time in a person's life where they are not
yet ready to receive תנחומין. Tanchumin. We know the משנה Mishnah in
פרקי אבות Pirkei Avot talks
about—it says that מתו מוטל לפניו, meto mutal lefanav, you can't wish
someone תנחומין. Tanchumin. So the period before the body has been buried,
we don't—a person isn't yet ready to receive consolation for that. So
it's a similar kind of thing, like don't try to wish someone
something at the wrong time.
Yeah, I want to make sure I understand. So this woman
was—the—she would have been the 22,000th person, right?
Right, the baby—the newborn.
That's my question. In other words, the עובר ubar would have been
the 22,000th, but not her.
Right. ראויה להשלים. reuya lehashlim. She being pregnant was going to fill
up
the amount, but not her herself, it was the עובר ubar itself,
it was the infant. Now, does it need to be 22,000 men?
No, I think women as well.
So exactly, so if there were 21,999, she was the second to
last person and then she was going to be משלים, mashlim, because
she counted as two.
Right.
Okay, so גמרא Gemara continues, last little bit of פרק מרובה. Perek
Merubah. אין פורסין נשבין ליוני. ein porsin nishvin leyonei. You cannot spread
traps for doves within—the משנה Mishnah had said within 30 ריס. ris.
30 ריס ris is equivalent to four מיל, mil, which is a
little bit less than four of our miles.
Four מיל mil is the distance a normal person could walk in
about 72 minutes. We know that because of all the questions about
when is צאת הכוכבים tzeit hakochavim and things like that. So you
cannot spread traps for the doves within 30 ריס, ris, that is,
four מיל mil of the city. Because presumably people who live in
the city keep their dove cotes within a short walk of the
city. If you spread traps near the city, you'll be catching other
people's doves. At least there's a concern there that you'll be stealing
the doves from other people. So the גמרא Gemara says, ומי אזלי
כולי האי, umi azlei kulei hai, do you really need to travel
so far?
That is, do the doves themselves travel so far that you have
to travel even farther to escape
beyond—beyond their reach? והתנן מרחיקין את השובך מן העיר חמישים אמה. vehatnan
marchikin et hashovach min ha'ir chamishim amah. When you build a dove
cote you have to just make sure it's only 50 אמה amah
away from the city. אמר אביי משאט שאט יתבו הכרסיהו בחמישים אמה
מעליא ומשלשים ריס. amar Abaye mishat shat yatvu karsaihu bechamishim amah malya
umishloshim ris.
So basically the first 50 אמה, amah, that's when the birds are
hungry and they're going to come and eat stuff, so you have
to make sure that they're not within 50 אמה amah of the
city that they're not going to come and eat. people's food. But
beyond that, once they've eaten their fill and they're full of food,
then they'll fly even up to four four miles, 30 ריס ris
beyond. So there's how much space around the dove-cote do the birds
need to find food, and then there's an even larger space where
they're willing to fly. They only eat close to where they live,
but they'll fly farther away. ותו, Ve-tu, but is that really true?
והתניא, Ve-hatanya, בישוב, be-yishuv, even מאה מיל me'ah mil לא יפרוס. lo
yifros.
There's another opinion in the ברייתא braita that says within a settled
area you cannot spread the nets to catch the doves even within
one hundred מיל. mil. One hundred מיל mil is a very far
distance. If four מיל mil takes 72 minutes, so it's 25 times
that distance.
That's a full day's worth of travel. I mean 24 hours of
walking. That's like a two or three days' journey, depending on how
much of the day you walk. והתניא בישוב ואפילו מאה מיל לא
יפרוס. Ve-hatanya be-yishuv ve-afilu me'ah mil lo yifros.
רב יוסף אמר בישוב כרמים. Rav Yosef amar be-yishuv kramim. No, it's
talking specifically about בישוב כרמים, be-yishuv kramim, an area that's not a
settled area that's populated, but a settled area where there are vineyards.
That is, if there are vineyards around, the birds can stop off
and rest and then pick up again and fly more. And then
stop and rest and then pick up and fly more. So obviously
they could travel much farther. They could travel even one hundred מיל.
mil. רבה אמר בישוב שובכין, Rabba amar be-yishuv shovachin,
or alternatively, it's an area where there are many dove-cotes and the
doves could go and find a place to rest and then they'll
again, it's like dove motel. So they'll fly step by step. ותיפוק
ליה משום שובכין גופייהו, Ve-teipok lei mishum shovachin gufaihu, so then maybe
you should just mention it regarding the fact that there are the
dove-cotes themselves. איבעית אימא, Ei ba'it eima, alternatively, בעובדי כוכבים, be-ovdei chochavim,
perhaps this is a difference between regarding Jewish dove-cotes that we have
to provide an even farther distance, that is the four מיל mil
compared to non-Jewish dove where we only care about fifty אמה. ama.
ואיבעית אימא, Ve-ei ba'it eima,
בהפקר, be-hefker, or regarding ownerless doves, in which case there should be
no concern of catching them and therefore you could even go closer.
ואיבעית אימא, Ve-ei ba'it eima, בדידיה, be-didai, or if they were yours.
So you could spread nets close to your own doves because then
whatever you're going to catch, either you'll catch wild ones or you'll
catch your own, but you're not going to catch anybody else's. הדרן
עלך מרובה, Hadran alach Meruba, now we're continuing with פרק החובל. Perek
Ha-chovel. We turn the דף, daf, פג עמוד ב. peh-gimmel amud bet.
We start a whole new discussion.
The concern with the dove-cotes and the distance is about theft of
other people's doves or is it about the noise and the mess?
I think it's about the theft and that's why the concern there
is that we don't have to, and again, this is more לפנים
משורת הדין lifnim mishurat ha-din kind of thing. Because again, doves, raising
doves, it's not like each little dove has a tag attached to
it that says belongs to who. You know, there's a sense of
people, the doves know where to come home at night, so you
own whatever ones come home to your dove-cote.
Yeah, they had that case where they find a dove on the
ground and if one leg is on one side, one leg is
on the other, and it's an ownership...
Right, it's all about ownership. Same thing here. So this is a
sense of, and that's exactly the point about the עובדי כוכבים. ovdei
chochavim. Even an idolater, there are different rules regarding how much or
how little it's appropriate to steal from non-Jews. Obviously it's not appropriate
to steal from them, but how far beyond the letter of the
law, how much לפנים משורת הדין lifnim mishurat ha-din do we have
to consider regarding non-Jews? Perhaps a lower threshold than we would have
for Jews. That is, the relationship within the Jewish community might demand
keeping farther distance, like good neighborliness is different than what would be
between a Jewish person and a non-Jewish person at that time, correct.
The first six chapters of בבא קמא Bava Kama had been about
mostly
נזקי ממון, nizkei mamon, damages caused by your property with some discussion
of אדם המזיק, adam ha-mazik, a person who themselves causes damage. The
seventh פרק perek we saw, פרק מרובה, Perek Meruba, dealt with גניבה,
gneiva, theft, and then also had extended discussions about all other sorts
of topics. And now פרק החובל, Perek Ha-chovel, we return to אדם
המזיק, adam ha-mazik, the damages caused by a person. The משנה mishna
begins. החובל בחבירו, Ha-chovel be-chaveiro, if a person punches another person, חייב
עליו משום חמישה דברים. chayav alav mishum chamisha devarim. There are five
things that you have to pay back.
נזק, nezek, actual damage caused. We're going to see how that's evaluated.
Each of these we're going to be major discussion, how do we
evaluate each of these five things? How does the בית דין beit
din assess to determine? Because you hear about crazy court cases nowadays.
Someone gets a cup of coffee and they spill it on themselves
and they say the coffee was too hot and they sue the
company and they get ten million dollars. So obviously spilling hot cup
of coffee on your lap is probably not worth ten million dollars.
So we're going to have to see how these things are assessed.
So the גמרא Gemara says נזק, nezek, צער, tza'ar, צער tza'ar is
the pain and suffering. ריפוי, ripui, medical
expenses. שבת, shevet, time off of work and בושת. boshet. בושת boshet
is embarrassment. So each of these is now going to be explicated
by the משנה. mishna. משנה mishna says בנזק כיצד? Be-nezek keitzad? So
what does it mean נזק? nezek? סימא את עינו, sima et eino,
קטע את ידו, kata et yado, if you blinded someone's eye or
you chopped off someone's hand, שיבר את רגלו, shiber et raglo, or
you broke his foot, רואים אותו כאילו הוא עבד. ro'im oto ke'ilu
hu eved. You consider what if this person were being sold... sold
as a slave right now. So עבד נמכר בשוק, eved nimkar bashuk,
being sold in the marketplace, ושמין כמה היה יפה וכמה הוא יפה.
v'shamin kama haya yafe v'kama hu yafe. You see how much this
person would have been worth beforehand as a slave and how much
he would have been worth afterwards. And that's the difference in value.
We don't say how much is a hand worth. We saw this
already discussed when we talked about the assessment of properties here too.
Okay.
Oh, it's in the next. Oh, the ArtScroll started now. Oh here,
there's one right here Dave.
Is it the one in there?
Well these are all Hebrew. What's this? Oh
this is the whole thing, no
that's two, that's also volume one.
This is volume three started.
So then I'll try to explain very clearly. Okay. So the point
of נזק nezek is that it is evaluated by taking the difference
of two prices, that is how much this person would be worth
as a slave now and how much they would have been worth
as a slave before the injury. And you subtract. That's the way
it's assessed and that's meant to be a קולא, kula, that's meant
to be a leniency regarding the amount paid. Generally we try to
find leniencies in these assessments because you're trying to take somebody's money
away. If we're trying to take somebody's money away, we have to
be lenient. We can't take too much money away. Okay, the next
one, צער. tza'ar. So how do we assess צער? tza'ar? כוואו בשפוד
או במסמר. kveo b'shipud o b'masmer. What if I puncture someone, I
stab them with something very sharp like a needle or a nail?
So that doesn't leave any actual permanent injury. All it does is
cause pain because it penetrates directly into the flesh. It's not like
chopping off someone's finger or hand. So in that case, אפילו על
ציפורנו, afilu al tziporno, even if it's underneath their fingernail, which we
know hurts a lot. That's how they test if people are alive,
is they check their reflex by sticking a needle under their fingernail.
Okay, אפילו על ציפורנו, afilu al tziporno, מקום שאינו עושה חבורה, makom
she-eino oseh chavura, a place where it doesn't leave any permanent injury.
So אומדין כמה אדם כיוצא בזה רוצה ליטול. omdin kama adam kayotzei
baze rotze litol. We would assess how much they would want to
get paid to undergo such a painful procedure, that is this is
like some of these game shows that say, well, you know, if
you let this guy hit you with a hammer then we'll pay
you, you know, ten thousand dollars or something like that. So again,
we would have to see how much a reasonable person would be
willing to undergo this kind of pain and suffering in order to
earn some cash.
כיוצא בזה רוצה ליטול להיות מצטער כך. kayotzei baze rotze litol l'hiyot
mitzta'er kach.
I don't want to be annoying, but על ציפורנו al tziporno means
underneath as opposed to on?
Perhaps on the nail, but then it's hard to understand what that
means exactly.
So the prepositions really are very fluid.
I'm not sure, or maybe it means on the fingernail and the
point is exactly the opposite, not that it's a sensitive area but
actually that it's a very resistant area and that
no, that if a person stabbed me on my fingernail, I would
only get a very, very little amount of צער tza'ar because there's
no pain involved.
But something's going on with a litmus test.
Yes, that's for sure. ריפוי, ripuy, what about medical expense? So הכהו,
hikahu, if you hit him, חייב לרפותו. chayav l'rapoto. You are obligated
to pay for, it's not explicit, you're obligated to heal, heal that
person. We obviously understand there's some people who are trained in how
to heal and there's some people who don't know how to heal.
So you hire someone who's capable of doing that, but it's not
explicit in the משנה. Mishna. So עלו בו צמחים, alu bo tzmachim,
if some kind of disease or scab grows up afterwards, אם מחמת
המכה חייב, im machamat hamaka chayav, שלא מחמת המכה פטור. shelo מחמת
המכה פטור shelo machamat hamaka patur. So if there's some kind of
further complication or gangrene or something like that, if it's because of
the initial injury then that's within the purview of the initial damage,
but if it's for a totally separate reason then the person who
caused damage is exempt. So חייתה ונסתרה, chayeta v'nistara, what if it
healed and then it got worse again? חייתה ונסתרה, chayeta v'nistara, and
healed and it got worse again, חייב לרפותו. chayav l'rapoto. You're still
obligated to heal it because that's still part of the continuation of
the initial injury. חייתה כל צרכה, chayeta kol tzorka, but if it
fully healed, אינו חייב לרפותו. eino chayav l'rapoto. Then if it gets
worse after that, that is if it fully healed and then something
else happened, at that point the person can always claim well yeah,
but it fully healed already, so it must be something else. Okay,
interesting point in a מחלוקת machloket between רש״י Rashi and the רא״ש
Rosh just about the question of נזק, nezek, that is the נזק
nezek is evaluated by the slave market. רש״י Rashi thinks that refers
to the עבד עברי. eved Ivri.
עבד עברי, eved Ivri, a person sells indentures themselves for six year
term of service, הלכה halacha which doesn't apply anymore, but we would
assess it based on עבד עברי. eved Ivri. And the רא״ש Rosh
says no, it's totally different, you should be based on the עבד
כנעני eved Kena'ani market, the non-Jewish slave market, because that's how much
a person's body is assessed to actually have value.
How can it possibly be an עבד עברי? eved Ivri? He's not
even a מכירה, mechira, right?
Not even a sale. So that's exactly the רא״ש's Rosh question on
רש״י. Rashi. So that's just an interesting מחלוקת machloket to note. The
other important thing to note here about ריפוי, ripuy, medical expenses, the
רא״ש Rosh has an important note for all of us. The רא״ש
Rosh says if the person got some complication from their injury because
they didn't listen to the doctor, then that's not the person who
caused the damage's fault. That's the person's responsibility, that is once the
doctor... He tells you the right way to get better, you have
to listen to your doctor. It's important to note, you know, many
of the ראשונים Rishonim were doctors, things like that, so it's as
as my רבי Rebbi once told me, he says הלכה halacha has
a love affair with medicine. So okay, medicine's a good thing. He
says שבת, shevet, what does it mean שבת? shevet? What is time
off of work? רואים אותו כאילו הוא שומר קישואים. ro'im oto k'ilu
hu shomer kishu'im. We consider that person as if they have the
minimal job that they have. This is a הלכתי halachic sense of
minimum wage. That is what's the minimum wage, or the normal baseline
wage? שומר קישואים, shomer kishu'im, a person who is the watchman for
a field of cucumbers or a field of squashes of some kind.
Presumably they have to keep the birds away, but probably not thieves
or anything like that because not a very valuable produce. So interestingly
enough field of cucumbers or field of squashes, קישואים, kishu'im, comes up
in the discussion in סנהדרין Sanhedrin about
כישוף, kishuf, that is magical incantations. Many of the תנאים Tannaim seem
to have had magical incantations about creating squashes out of nowhere.
So also an interesting סוגיא. sugya. Okay, so שבת, shevet, שכבר נתן
לו דמי ידו ודמי רגלו. shekvar natan lo d'mei yado u'd'mei raglo.
Because he was already paid for
the
actual injury to the hand or to the foot, and that's the
reason he's not working, you only assess him at a minimum wage.
Because the minimum wage is now that he's already been compensated for
the limb. But presumably that takes into account the fact that the
minimum wage really should be higher if you didn't pay the two
possibilities. You either pay a person time off of the job they
normally have or that they're normally capable of doing, but then you're
not worried about compensating them for the actual injury because the amount
of work that they can do day by day with a good
hand is however much. In this case, הלכה halacha says
you
compensate them for the injured hand and then at that point
you don't have to pay them the wage of the job that
they were already doing, you pay them a minimum wage. So just
an interesting question.
How do you compute that for all the years that they in
the future that they might earn?
No, the amount of time that they're off of work at all.
That is, this person is sitting at home doing nothing recovering from
their injury.
But if he lost a hand and he's no longer going to
be able to do that work? Right. Are you paying him for
like 20 years?
So my assumption from what you're explaining is
that's the valuation on the slave market. In other words, here's this
guy with two good hands,
I'm
going to get 40 years out of him doing the following job,
I'm going to pay this amount of money. So that's the formula
for factoring in what you're describing, okay right.
So we have a few more minutes, let's try to okay, and
בושת, boshet, important point, בושת הכל לפי המבייש והמתבייש. boshet hakol lefi
ham'vayesh v'hamit'bayesh. The amount of embarrassment involved in any injury is how
much the person causing the embarrassment and how much about the person
who got embarrassed. That is, if someone very important makes fun of
me, that's more embarrassing than if someone very low in our social
hierarchy makes fun of me because I'll say who cares what he
says, but if it's someone very important, I would care a lot.
The גמרא Gemara is now going to go into an extended conversation
of one of the most historically important topics in all of Judaism
and all of understanding the תורה, Torah, which is what does it
mean עין תחת עין. ayin tachat ayin. We know that the, what's
called in Latin, Lex Talionis, the reciprocal or
retaliatory law is about repayment in הלכה. halacha. That is, if you
injure someone, you have to pay them back, not by blinding their
eye, but by paying money.
How did הלכה halacha get to that point? Is it obviously in
some sense a rejection of the norms of the Near Eastern society
at the time? We know that עין תחת עין ayin tachat ayin
appears in Hammurabi's Code and other kind of Eastern law codes as
well.
And so how does this end? This then later becomes obviously a
central point of polemic against Christians and against קראים. Karaites. Christians because
the Christian New Testament talks about instead of an eye for an
eye, rather turn the other cheek, that is don't worry about retaliation
at all. And obviously הלכה, halacha, we don't care about retaliation, but
we do care about compensation. We care about financial restitution for injuries.
And the קראים Karaites took it very literally: if you hurt someone's
eye, we're going to hurt you in the eye. That kind of
a thing. And הלכה halacha rejects that as well. So it becomes
a central point of polemic against Christian interpretation and Karaitic interpretation. And
it's one of the things that's considered to be דברים המקובלים מפי
משה רבינו devarim ham'kubalim mipi Moshe Rabbeinu that we take this not
literally. But we're going to have to see how the... The גמרא
Gemara says, אמאי? Amai? עין תחת עין Ayin Tachat Ayin אמר רחמנא.
Amar Rachmana. So why do you have to pay back five things?
The תורה Torah says עין תחת עין, Ayin Tachat Ayin, you pay
an eye for an eye. But what does that mean? So אימא
עין ממש, Eima ayin mamash, maybe it means really you take your
eye out and you give it to someone. So לא סלקא דעתך
דתניא, Lo salka daitach de-tanya, יכול סימא עינו מסמא את עינו, Yachol
sima eino mesamei et eino, קטע ידו מקטע את ידו, Kata yado
mekateia et yado, does that really mean if someone blinds my eye
I have to blind their eye or if they cut off my
hand we have to cut off their hand? שיבר רגלו משבר את
רגלו, Shiber raglo meshaber et raglo, they broke my foot so we're
going to break his foot? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, מכה אדם ומכה
בהמה. Makeh adam u-makeh behema. We compare a person who strikes a
person to a person who strikes an animal. מה מכה בהמה לתשלומין,
Ma makeh behema letashlumin, if you injure an animal, obviously it doesn't
even make sense to there's no reciprocity there between an animal and
a human being, you just pay back the damage. If I hurt
your cow, so I have to pay you how much damage I
caused. אף מכה אדם לתשלומין, Af makeh adam letashlumin, therefore if a
person injures a human being, you also just pay back financial restitution
and there's no sense of actual injury involved.
By the way, I just want to see really quickly that you
said this as fast as fantastically powerful, that the קשיא אמאי Kashya
Amai is on the entire משנה. Mishna.
The entire משנה, Mishna, why do you pay back anything?
This whole structure, it's really like a very powerful קשיא. Kashya.
Right. The קשיא Kashya is like what do we need from the
whole משנה, Mishna, the whole משנה Mishna should be irrelevant.
Right. Okay, and the גמרא Gemara continues, ואם נפשך לומר, Ve-im nafshacha
lomar, הרי הוא אומר, Harei hu omer, לא תקחו כופר לנפש רוצח
אשר הוא רשע למות. Lo tikchu kofer lenefesh rotzeiach asher hu rasha
lamut. So the פסוק Pasuk in פרשת מסעי Parshat Masei says, you
are not allowed to take כופר Kofer that is some kind of
a penalty payment in a case of a manslaughter case for a
person who is a רשע למות, Rasha lamut, a person who is
somehow at least partially liable for a capital crime, that is in
the case of manslaughter, you cannot take כופר Kofer rather he has
to go to the עיר מקלט, Ir Miklat, he has to go
to the refuge city. So לנפש רוצח אי אתה לוקח כופר, Lenefesh
rotzeiach i attah lokeach kofer, you cannot take כופר Kofer in a
capital crime. אבל אתה לוקח כופר לראשי איברים שאינם חוזרים. Aval attah
lokeach kofer lerashei evarim she-einam chozrim. You can take כופר Kofer in
the case not of a capital crime but in an injury. If
someone cut off my thumb, that is the end of the limb
that doesn't grow back. ראשי איברים שאינם חוזרים, Rashei evarim she-einam chozrim,
rather than say if they injured me in such a place where
it would heal, well then the נזק Nezek is going to be
less appreciable like the stabbing case. There's going to be צער, Tzaar,
there's going to be ריפוי, Ripui, but there's not going to be
נזק Nezek in the same way.
We don't know from this סוגיא Sugya so far if the תלמוד
Talmud has any sense of psychological damage that could be caused to
somebody else.
That is true, it might fall under צער, Tzaar,
causing a trauma to somebody, incapacitating the person.
It's a מחלוקת ראשונים Machloket Rishonim about how much is צער, Tzaar,
only the צער Tzaar that's caused, the suffering caused right now, the
physical pain right now, and how much is it the pain that
lasts over time. So that gets to the trauma question as well.
So היי מכה אילימא מכה בהמה ישלמנה ומכה אדם יומת. Hai makeh
eilima makeh behema yeshalmena u-makeh adam yumat. Which מכה? Makeh? The פסוק
Pasuk said מכה, Makeh, who hits someone? So which מכה Makeh are
we talking about? Is it the one from ויקרא Vayikra that said
מכה בהמה ישלמנה, Makeh behema yeshalmena, if you strike an animal you
pay it back, ומכה אדם יומת U-makeh adam yumat and if you
hit a person you should be put to death? ההוא בקטלא כתיב.
Hahu be-katala ktiv. That must be referring to hitting a person so
much that they die. Obviously we're not going to execute people for
punching people like if I punch someone in the face and they
get up, right? We know that from משפטים, Mishpatim, נפל למשכב, Nafal
lemishkav, if you get up again then obviously it's not a capital
crime. So what? So ההוא בקטלא כתיב. Hahu be-katala ktiv. That's talking
about a mortal wound that the person is going to die
from. אלא מהכא, Ela me-hacha, it must be from this פסוק, Pasuk,
מכה נפש בהמה ישלמנה נפש תחת נפש. Makeh nefesh behema yeshalmena nefesh
tachat nefesh. If you hit a בהמה Behema and you pay it
back, נפש תחת נפש Nefesh tachat nefesh and it's a life for
a life. But if it's a life for a life, דסמיך ליה
ואיש כי יתן מום בעמיתו כאשר עשה כן יעשה לו. De-samich lei
ve-ish ki yiten mum ba-amito ka-asher asa ken ye-aseh lo. And if
a person injures his friend, whatever he did should be paid back
to him. So there are all of these פסוקים Psukim that indicate
at the פשט Pshat level that we do retaliatory punishments, however, each
of them is within the context of paying back financial restitution for
injuries to animals. That's the point. And so therefore each of those
connections, תוספות Tosafot gets into the question, is it גזירה שוה Gezeirah
Shavah using the word מכה Makeh or is it סמוכים Smuchim that
is that they're just next to each other. There are different rules
about how some of those are applied. And a fascinating tangential question
which comes up in the נימוקי יוסף Nimukei Yosef in the back,
he quotes from the רא"ה, Ra'ah,
who was one of the students of the רשב"א Rashba in Spain.
So the רא"ה Ra'ah has a whole long discussion there and it's
within the רמב"ן's Ramban school of thought as well. By גזירה שוה
Gezeirah Shavah that is one of the principles of hermeneutics where the
same word appears in two פסוקים Psukim and we can connect them.
So we have a general principle אין אדם דן גזירה שוה לעצמו,
Ein adam dan gezeirah shavah le-atzmo, you can't make up your own
גזירה שוה Gezeirah Shavah because then what? The word זה Zeh and
the word זה Zeh is here both, the word אתה Attah and
the word אתה Attah so it's totally arbitrary. So obviously you could
make up whatever הלכות Halachot you wanted. That would be the case.
So it has to be from a קבלה. kabbalah. You have to
receive tradition from your teacher going back to his teacher going back.
But says the רא"ה Ra'ah interestingly enough, if you already know the
הלכה halacha and you're just trying to provide a mnemonic for it,
you could make up your own mnemonic גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. That
is, using the same words to help you remember the הלכה. halacha.
And it's important because רמב"ן Ramban in discussion of סוכה, Sukkah, the
הלכה halacha is מצטער פטור מן הסוכה. mitzta'er patur min hasukkah. A
person who's uncomfortable is obviously to what extent are you considered uncomfortable
enough to be exempt from the מצוה mitzvah of סוכה, Sukkah, but
the רמב"ן Ramban connects that to a פסוק pasuk from תהלים Tehillim
and a פסוק pasuk in the discussion of the סוכה Sukkah in
ויקרא. Vayikra. And so all these other ראשונים rishonim and אחרונים acharonim
ask, רמב"ן Ramban just made up a דרשה? drashah? There's no דרשה
drashah given in the גמרא, Gemara, it's just given as that הלכה
halacha and רמב"ן Ramban came up with his own דרשה. drashah. So
obviously it must be רמב"ן Ramban was the teacher of the teacher
of the teacher of the רא"ה, Ra'ah, the same tradition, that is
if it's just as a mnemonic, you're already taking an already established
law and just coming up with a way to help you remember
it, that that's okay. It's not making your own גזירה שוה gezeirah
shavah in that case. Okay. So what were we talking about? ואיש
כי יתן מום בעמיתו כאשר עשה כן יעשה לו. v'ish ki yitein
mum ba'amito ka'asher asah kein yei'aseh lo. So a person
who he injures his friend, whatever he did it should be done
back to him. האי לאו מכה הוא הכא הכא קאמרינן? hai lav
makeh hu hacha hacha kaamrinan? Is that not about actually just hitting
someone? Because it says כאשר עשה כן יעשה לו, ka'asher asah kein
yei'aseh lo, it sounds like reciprocity. So from that we have to
learn a דרשה drashah הכאה הכאה, haka'ah haka'ah, a גזירה שוה gezeirah
shavah or perhaps סמוכים smuchim using the word הכאה haka'ah about
hitting, קאמרינן. kaamrinan. מה הכאה האמורה בבהמה לתשלומין, mah haka'ah ha'amurah biveheimah
letashlumin, just like if you hit an animal it means for monetary
compensation. אף הכאה האמורה באדם לתשלומין. af haka'ah ha'amurah ba'adam letashlumin. Therefore
also hitting a person refers to monetary compensation. הכתיב ואיש כי יכה
כל נפש אדם מות יומת, haktiv v'ish ki yakeh kol nefesh adam
mot yumat, a person who hits another person should be put to
death. That's another פסוק. pasuk. So it must be בממון. bimamon. We
don't put you to death, we put your money to death. We
take your money away. So that obviously to a certain extent we
know ארבעה חשובים כמת. arba'ah chashuvim kemeit. One of the four people
who is considered to be as if dead in some sense is
עני, ani, a poor person. In some sense if they're really destitute,
in some sense is almost considered to be compared to a dead
person. So in a similar case here the הלכה halacha says מות
יומת, mot yumat, we're going to execute you, it doesn't mean execute,
it means we're going to take your money away.
But wait, I don't understand, why this פסוק, pasuk, the clear פשט
pshat is ואיש כי יכה כל נפש אדם מות יומת v'ish ki
yakeh kol nefesh adam mot yumat is a fatal injury.
Right. מכה נפש אדם. makeh nefesh adam.
You hit a person to their נפש אדם nefesh adam is a
fatal injury as opposed to the fatal injury to the בהמה beheimah
up above וסמוך v'samuch to the blemish that's caused to the his...
Exactly. So why why is the
גמרא Gemara going to ask a question? The גמרא Gemara says בממון
מאי בממון אימא במיתה ממש. bimamon mai bimamon eima bemitah mamash. So
maybe it's talking about really, it's about actually a mortal wound. וכי
תעלה על דעתך חדא דהאי תשלומי מכה בבהמה ישלמנה. vechi ta'aleh al
da'atach chada dehai tashlumei makeh biveheimah yeshalmenah. So on one side it's
connected to financial compensation for injuring an
animal. וכתיב בתריה כאשר יתן מום באדם כן ינתן בו, ukhtiv batreih
ka'asher yitein mum ba'adam kein yinnatein bo, that if you injure a
person it will be put back onto
you. שמע מינה shma minah ממון. mamon. It must be talking about
financial compensation. That is, it's bracketed on one side by injuring a
person. We have three cases basically. We're trying to figure out what
happens if you injure a person. Right. We know if you injure
an animal you pay back the value of the damage. We know
that if you kill a person you will be killed and we
don't just let you pay financial retribution, recompense. So the middle case,
injuring a person, is that more similar to killing a person or
is it more similar to injuring an animal? And that's the גמרא's
Gemara's next question. שמע מינה ממון ומאי נשח לומר תו לכאשר לתנא
מאי חזית דאלפת ממכה בהמה אלף ממכה אדם? shma minah mamon u'mai
nashach lomar tu l'ka'asher l'tanna mai chazit d'aleft mimakeh beheimah alef mimakeh
adam? Why should we learn it from מכה בהמה, makeh beheimah, hitting
an animal? We should learn it from מכה אדם, makeh adam, hitting
a person. So אמרי דנין נזיקין מנזיקין. amri danin nezikin minezikin. We
should learn damages from other damages. ואין דנין נזיקין ממיתה. ve'ein danin
nezikin mimmitah. We shouldn't learn damages from from fatal injuries, from a
death. So אדרבא דנינא אדם מאדם. aderaba danina adam mei'adam. We should
learn human case to another human case rather ואין דנינא אדם מבהמה.
ve'ein danina adam mibeheimah. And that's a great question on this whole
discussion. That is the whole time we've been trying to say injuring
a person we should learn from injuring an animal, it should be
financial compensation rather than retribution or retaliation as it is by capital
crime. But obviously we're trying to learn from an animal to a
human being rather than human being to human being. So that's the
conceptual question that's here. היינו דתני אם נשח לומר הרי הוא אומר
לא תקחו כופר לנפש רוצח אשר הוא רשע למות. hainu detani im
nashach lomar harei hu omer lo tikechu kofer lenefesh rotzei'ach asher hu
rasha lamut. So obviously, and that's why there's another prohibition on taking
financial כופר kofer in a case of a capital crime. כי ימות
ימות לנפש רוצח אי אתה לוקח כופר אבל אתה לוקח כופר לראשי
איברים שאינן חוזרים. ki yamut yamat lenefesh rotzei'ach i attah lokei'ach kofer
aval attah lokei'ach kofer l'rashei evarim she'einan chozrim. And therefore you can
take כופר, kofer, perhaps you're obligated to take כופר. kofer. for the
tips of the limbs which do not grow back. People have a
few minutes, we can go up until the two dots, I don't
mean to hold people too long. It's just a few more lines.
והאי לא תקחו כופר לנפש רוצח למעוטי ראשי איברים הוא Ve'hai lo
tikchu kofer lenefesh rotzeach lemautei rashei evarim hu? So is that really
what that פסוק pasuk comes to teach, that is, that the exemption
from כופר kofer by capital crime comes to include financial payment for
the tips of the limbs which don't grow
back? למעוטי. Lemautei. Exactly. To exclude, that is, you're allowed to pay
כופר kofer for limbs, injuries. האי מיבעי ליה דאמר רחמנא לא תעביד
ביה
תרתי.
Hai mibaye lei d'amar rachmana lo
ta'avid beih tarti. So you should do two things from it. Number
one: לא תשקול מיניה ממונא, lo tishkol minei mamona, that you should
not pay money from someone who has committed a capital crime, and
number two: וקטליה, u'katlei, and that you should kill them. That is,
there's a prohibition on taking כופר kofer and there's the obligation to
impose a death penalty. Both of those are learned now from that
same פסוק: pasuk: לא תקחו כופר לנפש רוצח
אשר הוא רשע למות.
Lo tikchu kofer lenefesh
rotzeach asher hu rasha lamut. Don't take כופר kofer because he deserves
death
penalty. Okay, האי מכדי רשעתו נפקא. Hai michdei rishato nafka. So maybe
you should learn that from כדי רשעתו kedei rishato according to his
crime, which is another פסוק pasuk from דברים. Devarim. דמיבעי ליה דאמר
רחמנא לא תשקול ממונא ותפטריה. D'mibaye lei d'amar rachmana lo tishkol mamona
u'tifterei. Do not take money to exempt this person. Again, the sense
that in a capital crime you cannot pay your way out. אם
כן לכתוב רחמנא לא תקחו כופר לאשר הוא רשע למות לנפש רוצח
למה לי
Im ken lichtov רחמנא rachmana lo tikchu kofer la'asher hu rasha
lamut lenefesh rotzeach lama li? The פסוק pasuk could have been phrased
differently. לנפש רוצח למה לי lenefesh rotzeach lama li? Why does it
say לנפש רוצח, lenefesh rotzeach, to a
murderer? שמע מינה לנפש רוצח אי אתה לוקח כופר אבל אתה לוקח
כופר לראשי איברים שאינם חוזרים. shma mina lenefesh rotzeach iy ata lokeach
kofer aval ata lokeach kofer lorashei evarim she'einam chozrim. You cannot take
כופר kofer in a murderer's case, but you can take כופר kofer
if limbs were injured. וכי מאחר דכתיב לא תקחו כופר מכה מכה
למה לי V'chi me'achar d'chtiv lo tikchu kofer makkeh makkeh lama li?
So then why do I have the גזרה שוה gezeirah shavah of
מכה מכה makkeh makkeh to connect it to the animal injuries?
אמרי אם מהאי הוה אמינא אי בעי עינו ניתיב ואי בעי דמי
עינו ניתיב.
Amrei im me'hai hava amina i ba'ei eino
nitiv v'i ba'ei dmei eino nitiv. I might have thought you get
two options. Number one, if you want to blind the person's eye,
you can blind the person's eye. Or, if they want to pay,
then they could pay, but it's always two options. But we don't
let you take the blinding the eye option. We prevent you from
doing that. קא משמע לן מבהמה מה מכה בהמה לתשלומים אף מכה
אדם לתשלומים. Ka mashma lan mi'behemah mah makkeh behemah l'tashlumin af makkeh
adam l'tashlumin.
You pay back a financial restitution and you're not allowed to actually
go and injure the other person.
The anthropological note before we end is that some people have suggested
even earlier in human history the way עין תחת עין ayin tachat
ayin evolved, that is, the actual direct damaging response evolved in Hammurabi's
code as a limit. That is, imagine someone cut off my hand
and my whole family is really bothered by that and they want
to get revenge. They're going to cut off his arm, they'll kill
the person, they'll burn down their house. It'll be escalation of violence.
So in Hammurabi's code, עין תחת עין ayin tachat ayin you could
read as רק עין תחת עין, rak ayin tachat ayin, limiting it.
The תורה Torah obviously takes it even further. That is, the rabbinic
tradition takes it not as yes, you're allowed to do exactly equal
retribution but no more. We see you're not even allowed to have
retribution, you have to just have monetary compensation. So that's where we
get up to today and tomorrow we'll continue with the פרק החובל.
Perek HaChovel.